<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Frozen Rockets Blog</title>
    <description>Frozen Rockets - freelance web design</description>
    <link>http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>99% of my clients don&#39;t ask for an accessible website, they just get one.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Accessibility still seems to be one of those things most designers and developers don’t want to think about. WAI Aria is a W3C Reccomendation since March of this year, but most websites I see don’t use Landmark roles, let alone Live Regions. And somehow, many developers don’t even care about semantic HTML anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if it’s just lazyness or that designers and developers see accessibility as an annoying constraint, but I guess it’s a combination of both. Just like testing a website in Internet Explorer is an annoyance, so is testing it with a screen reader. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason making websites accessible is still seen as something you do for &lt;em&gt;that one blind guy&lt;/em&gt;, but designing an accessible website means you design it for everybody. That includes &lt;a href=&quot;https://the-pastry-box-project.net/anne-gibson/2014-july-31&quot;&gt;your grandma who needs her reading glasses, a co-worker who broke his arm and your colorblind girlfriend&lt;/a&gt;, but also that person who tries to access you site on hotel wifi. That means readable text, keyboard navigation, underlined links and a site that works when Javascript fails to load.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I have worked on several government websites, which are obliged to comply with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.webrichtlijnen.nl/english/what-and-why/regulatory&quot;&gt;the Dutch Web Guidelines&lt;/a&gt; (WCAG 2.0), most of the accessibility work I do is for projects where it’s not one of the requirements. Most of my clients don’t even know. Or care, to be honest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess for many designers this lack of care translates to not having to care about it themselves. Most clients don’t give a damn if I use &lt;a href=&quot;/adding-aria-to-this-site/&quot;&gt;ARIA Roles&lt;/a&gt; or not or if choose to make something a &amp;lt;button&amp;gt; or an &amp;lt;a&amp;gt;, so I see this as a opportunity to do as much as I can to make it accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;doesnt-it-take-more-time&quot;&gt;Doesn’t it take more time?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, sometimes. Sometimes you need to do some extra work to make sure an element is &lt;em&gt;hoverable&lt;/em&gt;, or to do an extra check for color contrasts, but in my experience most issues can be resolved by just designing responsibly: using the correct HTML, picking a proper font size, making sure text zoom works, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know I lost years of my life debugging weird bugs in &lt;abbr title=&quot;Internet Explorer&quot;&gt;IE&lt;/abbr&gt;, sometimes things just take time. I consider it part of the job. At least making a client’s site more accessible is a much nicer and more gratifying part of the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alright-you-got-me-now-what&quot;&gt;Alright, you got me, now what?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are some of the tools I use to make my work a little easier. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/accessibility-developer-t/fpkknkljclfencbdbgkenhalefipecmb&quot;&gt; Accessibility Developer Tools&lt;/a&gt; (Chrome plugin)&lt;/strong&gt;, checks things like color contrast;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VoiceOver (Mac)&lt;/strong&gt; is built in to OS X and a great way to see how your site is read by a screen reader;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://squizlabs.github.io/HTML_CodeSniffer/&quot;&gt;HTML_CodeSniffer&lt;/a&gt; (Bookmarklet)&lt;/strong&gt;, a nice bookmarklet to check different conformance levels;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heydonworks.com/revenge_css_bookmarklet/&quot;&gt;Revenge.css&lt;/a&gt; (Bookmarklet)&lt;/strong&gt;, this bookmarklet will make it painfully clear where your site needs improvement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you include these tools into your workflow, you’ll see there are many quick-wins. Just start picking the low-hanging fruit and you’ll soon be making better websites without thinking about it. So please, designers and developers, I ask you to stop making a distinction between accessibility projects and &lt;em&gt;regular&lt;/em&gt; projects. If you make every website as accessible as possible, we all benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2014 08:50:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/clients-dont-ask-for-accessibility</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/clients-dont-ask-for-accessibility</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tablet first is not really a thing, right?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I work for a large variety of companies and agencies and one of the things I keep hearing, is something they call &lt;em&gt;Tablet First Design&lt;/em&gt;. Especially design agencies seem to sell this as a genuine approach. I first heard about &lt;em&gt;Tablet First&lt;/em&gt; about 2 years ago, but it seems to gain more traction lately and I wonder what it means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;Tablet First&lt;/em&gt; approach is derived from &lt;em&gt;Mobile First&lt;/em&gt;, the title of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.abookapart.com/products/mobile-first&quot;&gt;Luke Wroblewski’s book for A Book Apart&lt;/a&gt; and the name of the principle he coined. Mobile First is a design approach where you start with designing for &lt;em&gt;mobile&lt;/em&gt; (small screens) and utilizing the device’s capabilities. The reasoning behind this approach is that the contraints force you to focus on what’s necessary for the user to achieve his task. That way you get rid of all the unnecessary cruft that you normally see on websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before Mobile First came along &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hesketh.com/thought-leadership/our-publications/progressive-enhancement-and-future-web-design&quot;&gt;Progressive Enhancement was mostly a technical thing&lt;/a&gt;, but Luke took it a step further and applied these principles to design as well. Serve &lt;em&gt;mobile&lt;/em&gt; users with the best version of the site for mobile and build upon this for devices with more capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-tablet-first&quot;&gt;What is tablet first?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When compared to smartphones, tablets have 3 important characteristics in common: touchscreens, sensors and portability. Just like for smartphones these characteristics are not binary; it’s not a matter of true/false and yes or no,  each device has varying support levels. a Samsung Note is more portable than an iPad Mini, which is more portable than a Surface. The same goes for screens, from black-and-white resistive touchscreens to 4k screens. These traits are &lt;a href=&quot;http://adactio.com/journal/6692/&quot;&gt;inherent to the web as a continuum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to serve tablets with a &lt;em&gt;Tablet First&lt;/em&gt; design, we have to consider the unpredictable nature of the web and the best way to do that is by using progressive enhancement. Start with designing for the least capable devices, and build upon this when possible and necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimizing for tablets does not mean optimizing for the iPad Air. A &lt;em&gt;tablet user&lt;/em&gt; might just as well be an e-book reader with a black-and-white screen and a low refresh rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-it-the-screen&quot;&gt;Is it the screen?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tablets tend to have smaller screens than desktop computers (except &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.laptopmag.com/reviews/tablets/toshibaexcite13&quot;&gt;sometimes they don’t&lt;/a&gt;). So it might be a layout that’s built for a 1024x768 resolution, which is the resolution for iPads, but that’s not &lt;em&gt;Tablet First&lt;/em&gt;, that’s &lt;em&gt;iPad First&lt;/em&gt;. Or &lt;em&gt;2005 First&lt;/em&gt; because not that long ago we were all designing for was the most common resolution for desktop computers. I don’t think screen size is a good criterium as long as nobody can tell me if this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sonymobile.com/nl/products/phones/xperia-z-ultra/&quot;&gt;6.4” Sony Experia&lt;/a&gt; is a phone or a tablet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So maybe it’s optimizing for touchscreens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does that mean? Big hit-areas for links and buttons to make it touch-friendly? You could easily call that &lt;a href=&quot;https://signalvnoise.com/posts/1048-padded-link-targets-for-better-mousing&quot;&gt;basic usability&lt;/a&gt;. It was already recommended before the iPad was unveiled. If anything, I’d call it touch-friendly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so it’s not about screens then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sensors-then&quot;&gt;Sensors then?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it might be about GPS, accelerometers, luminosity sensors and all these other cool things that are built into smartphones and tablets. As we’ve seen before the web is an unpredictable medium. You can’t rely on these sensors to be present, so you need to have a fallback, or rather enhance when they are present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t see this being any different for tablets than it is for mobile or even desktop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;it-must-be-the-portability-then&quot;&gt;It must be the portability then.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The portability of tablets effects its usage in 2 ways. You can 1) take it with you so you can use the GPS for location-based functionality and 2) you can hold it in your hands which can be used to create a ”submersive experience”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first effect is already discussed in the previous section. The second one is not that different from phones or dektops. If you disagree I advise you to look around in public transportation, most people are looking at their phones. How’s that for submersive?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-whats-left&quot;&gt;So what’s left?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest advantages of &lt;em&gt;Mobile First&lt;/em&gt; are the constraints. They force you to focus on the actual content and the primary goal of a page. Just like Stephen Hay mentions in his book &lt;a href=&quot;http://responsivedesignworkflow.com/&quot;&gt;Responsive Design Workflow&lt;/a&gt; ’start designing from the content out’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mobile First is not about layout, but it’s about designing &lt;em&gt;Content First&lt;/em&gt; and progressive enhancement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t see how Tablet First adds anything to that approach. If it’s about designing for smaller than 1600x1200 and large hit-areas, we already have a name for that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s called web design.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2014 20:05:01 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/tablet-first-is-not-a-thing</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/tablet-first-is-not-a-thing</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Please stop doing this</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Please stop with: This is a 2 minute read. Scroll hijacking. Seemingly randomly arranged blocks with photos. “Hamburger”-icons. “Hamburger”-icons on desktopsites. “Hamburger”-icons with a popup to explain. Loooooooong single-page sites. Any single-page site. Full window parallax scrolling images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peek-a-boo navigation bars. “Turn off your ad-blocker to see the content”. Pages that transition when you first load them. Sites that all try to look like Medium. Loading screens. Fixed navigation that looks like cookie warnings. Full window autoplaying video. An input-field with the URL underneath an article. Disabled zooming on mobile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course: Social sharing icons. Carousels. Please download our app. Endless scrolling. Loading screens, seriously? Still? Fixed-width websites. Only being able to login with Facebook. 7 things you probably didn’t know about sharks. Low contrast text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2014 15:31:51 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/stop-doing-this</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/stop-doing-this</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Difficult doesn&#39;t need to be complex</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;About 2 months ago I had the pleasure of attending the Beyond Tellerrand conference in Düsseldorf and watching many great talks by Ethan Marcotte, Erik Spiekermann, Jessica Hische and others. The one that stood out to me, was Stephen Hay’s talk titled Maintaining Simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great way to achieve simplicity and one of the key principles in his work and in this talk is the &lt;em&gt;Zero Interface&lt;/em&gt;, the concept where there is no interface between the user and the goal she is trying to accomplish. Whatever the user thinks of, with the snap of a finger the result is there. Think Amazon 1-Click without even clicking a button. This hypothetical (and perhaps ideal) interface can help us reduce complexity in the interfaces we design when we remember that “&lt;em&gt;anything you add to the zero interface is perhaps one step too many&lt;/em&gt;” (from &lt;a href=&quot;http://responsivedesignworkflow.com&quot;&gt;Responsive Design Workflow&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love this concept, because it forces us to make things as simple as possible. Somehow there’s a misconception that designing a simple interface is easier and takes less work than making something complex. It’s true that most complex interfaces are the result of years of work and new implementations, but obviously not a lot of work has gone into thinking and considering each addition to the interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;difficult-vs-complex&quot;&gt;Difficult vs. Complex&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When making the distinction between something difficult and something complicated, I like the Marathon Analogy: Running a marathon is very difficult, it takes a lot of training and you’ll  feel exhausted when you cross the finishline, but it’s not complicated; Just put one foot in front of the other. For 42 kilometers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have to do something difficult, at least make it simple to do it. This is true for running marathons and it’s also true for interfaces. I’ve worked on a project where the best regarded content managers were the ones who actually knew how to operate the CMS. It felt like a badge of honor to them. That’s just crazy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Stephen mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/stephenhay/the-zero-interface-using-zero-based-thinking-to-maintain-simplicity-fowd-london-2014&quot;&gt;his talk&lt;/a&gt;: “&lt;em&gt;Simple doesn’t mean stupid (and complex doesn’t mean smart)&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 15:31:51 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/difficult-doesnt-need-to-be-complex</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/difficult-doesnt-need-to-be-complex</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Adding ARIA landmark roles to my site</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently launched my new website along with a new visual identity. I left some work to be done on purpose, so I could document these enhancements afterwards. This first step is to add WAI-ARIA roles to the site to further improve the usability for visitors who use assistive technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-first-what-is-wai-aria&quot;&gt;But first, what is WAI-ARIA?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WAI-ARIA (which I’ll call ARIA from now on) is short for ‘Web Accessibility Initiative – Accessible Rich Internet Applications’. It is a set of attributes that can be added as a layer on top of HTML to provide extra information about the semantics of the site to screen readers and other assistive technologies. Among other things, ARIA enhances accessibility of interactive controls (such as drag and drop and sliders), provides roles for page structure (“landmarks” for navigation, search and main content) and areas for dynamic content (called “live regions” in ARIA).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-adding-aria-roles&quot;&gt;About adding ARIA roles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, let’s start with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3.org/TR/aria-in-html/#first-rule-of-aria-use&quot;&gt;the first rule of ARIA&lt;/a&gt;: “The first rule of ARIA, is don’t use ARIA.”
If you can use a native HTML element or attribute with the semantics and behaviour you require already built in, instead of re-purposing an element and adding an ARIA role, state or property to make it accessible, then do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, that’s what I did, of course, and I hope everyone does.
This site uses structural elements like &amp;lt;header&amp;gt; and &amp;lt;main&amp;gt; and it doesn’t have that many interactions. There’s a navigation menu, a contactform and some links, nothing really exiting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I’ll only focus on ARIA Landmarks in this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;low-hanging-fruit&quot;&gt;Low hanging fruit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what the site looks like now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/assets/screenshot-frozenrockets-about.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of the Frozen Rockets about page&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the quick wins. Since HTML5 provided us with new structural elements, there is some clear overlap between ARIA roles and native HTML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://html5doctor.com/the-main-element/&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;main&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; element&lt;/a&gt; is the main content of the page (for this page it would contain this article) and it should only be used once in a document. This directly maps to the &lt;em&gt;main&lt;/em&gt;-role in ARIA and in the future you wouldn’t have to use this role if you use &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;main&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, but because of the lack of support in Internet Explorer and some of the mobile browsers and to maximize compatibility, we’ll add it like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;main&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;role=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;main&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up is the &lt;em&gt;sidebar&lt;/em&gt;, which contains the logo, a large background image and a navigation menu. This sidebar is a &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;header&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; element and it’s site-oriented, rather than page-specific. The ARIA role to use for this is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3.org/TR/wai-aria/roles#banner&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;banner&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a banner usually appears at the top of the page and typically spans the full width, but in this case it sits next to the content (on desktop).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the &lt;em&gt;main&lt;/em&gt;-role, a banner should only mark one element in the document, so that makes it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;header&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;role=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;banner&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;sidebar&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;navigation&quot;&gt;Navigation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look a the navigation now. There’s a navigation menu in the bottom-left corner and some links to deeper-lying pages. The bottom-left navigation is an obvious candidate for the &lt;em&gt;navigation&lt;/em&gt;-role, which represents a collection of navigational elements (usually links) for navigating the document or related documents. It maps to the HTML &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;nav&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; element, so that makes it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;nav&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;role=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;navigation&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;ol&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;./projects&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Projects&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;./about&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;About Frozen Rockets&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;http://blog.frozenrockets.nl&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Articles&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;./contact.php&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Contact&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/ol&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/nav&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The navigation landmark can be used more than once on a page, but don’t overdo it. Not any list of links is a navigation landmark, just like you probably wouldn’t wrap it in a &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;nav&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;-element. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these roles in place, the main structure of the pages is done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/assets/screenshot-frozenrockets-about-aria-roles.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of the Frozen Rockets about page with ARIA-roles in place&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;that-leaves-us-with&quot;&gt;That leaves us with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the low hanging fruit out of the way, there are still 4 other roles left to consider:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contentinfo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Complementary&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Form&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Search&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;search&quot;&gt;Search&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll start with the easy one: &lt;em&gt;Search&lt;/em&gt; (role=search). As you probably guessed, this is for forms that let you search or filter the content on the site. There is nothing like that on the site, so I’ll skip that one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;contentinfo&quot;&gt;Contentinfo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spec says: “A large perceivable region that contains information about the parent document.Examples of information included in this region of the page are copyrights and links to privacy statements.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have a footer on the site that might contain this info, but there is &lt;a href=&quot;http://frozenrockets.nl/credits&quot;&gt;a page that I link to from the homepage with copyright information&lt;/a&gt;. I’ll apply this role to the link on the homepage like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;./credits&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;role=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;contentinfo&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Credits&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;complementary&quot;&gt;Complementary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3.org/TR/wai-aria/roles#complementary&quot;&gt;According to the spec&lt;/a&gt;, this is “a supporting section of the document, designed to be complementary to the main content at a similar level in the DOM hierarchy, but remains meaningful when separated from the main content.” Pretty much the same as the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;aside&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have anything like that on my site right now, so I can skip that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;form&quot;&gt;Form&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A landmark region that contains a collection of items and objects that, as a whole, combine to create a form.” The most obvious thing to do is just add the role to any form on your site, but the semantics for this role already apply to the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;form&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;-element, so that would be redundant. If (and you probably shouldn’t) you don’t use the native &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;form&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;-element for a form, this role would be applied to the containing &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;div&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;done&quot;&gt;Done&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the ARIA-roles in place, I’ve made my website a bit more accessible. There is some work left for the contactform, which I’ll leave for a next article about ARIA states.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2014 16:24:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/adding-aria-to-this-site</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/adding-aria-to-this-site</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Customizing your HTML5 form validation messages</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Using the &lt;em&gt;title&lt;/em&gt;-attribute for input-fields is, of course, recommended when you want to provide your visitors with some extra information besides the text in the &amp;lt;label&amp;gt;, something like ‘Please enter your full name’ would be a lot more useful and accessible than just asking for “Name”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed not many people are aware of this extra feature of the title-attribute, but if you use the &lt;em&gt;title&lt;/em&gt;-attribute, this text will also appear in the error message when you use HTML5 form validation (which you do use, right?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;label&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	Name
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;input&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;required&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;text&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;title=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Please enter your full name&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/label&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this doesn’t work in Firefox, but you can easily fix that with the non-standard x-moz-errormessage attribute:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;label&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	Name
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;input&lt;/span&gt; 	&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;required&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;text&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;title=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Please enter your full name&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;x-moz-errormessage=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Please enter your full name&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/label&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This works across modern browsers (Chrome, Firefox, Opera and IE 10+), let’s hope Safari 8 joins the party this fall.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2014 00:03:46 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/customizing-your-html5-form-validation-messages</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/customizing-your-html5-form-validation-messages</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The new face of Frozen Rockets</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m proud to finally present the new identity and website of Frozen Rockets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months ago I asked my friend and awesome designer &lt;a href=&quot;http://stephancsikos.nl&quot;&gt;Stephan Csikós&lt;/a&gt; to work on a new brand identity for me. I’m very pleased with the result he came up with. Seriously, if you need a great graphic designer or art director, hire him!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on his work, I designed this website, where I ‘practice what I preach’, so of course it’s completely keyboard-accessible and it conforms to &lt;i&gt;WCAG 2.0&lt;/i&gt; (accessibility) standards without it being ‘boring’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll go into more details about some of the design choices and implementations on this site in more detail in some follow-up articles later, but if you like to look around, feel free to check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/petervangrieken/Frozenrockets.nl-new&quot;&gt;the source code on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. Also, if you run into any issues, &lt;a href=&quot;./../contact.php&quot;&gt;please let me know&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great thing about the web is that it can be changed at any time, so I deliberately left some work to be done (like adding ARIA roles), which I’ll cover in upcoming articles on this site.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2014 15:31:51 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/the-new-face-of-frozen-rockets</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.frozenrockets.nl/the-new-face-of-frozen-rockets</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
